From zero to hero.
The Mask is a romance, comedy, crime film directed by Chuck Russell.
Stanley, a meek bank employee, turns into an eccentric and maniacal green-skinned superhero who can bend
reality, after wearing a wooden mask that was created by Loki, the Norse god of mischief.
Stanley Ipkiss / The Mask, played by Jim Carrey.
Mitch Kellaway, played by Peter Riegert.
Dorian Tyrrell, played by Peter Greene.
Peggy Brandt, played by Amy Yasbeck.
Charlie Schumaker, played by Richard Jeni.
Niko, played by Orestes Matacena.
The Mask is a 1994 American superhero slapstick film loosely based on the
1991 comic book series by John Arcudi and Doug Mahnke.
Directed by Chuck Russell and written by Mike Werb, the film stars Jim Carrey, Peter
Riegert, Peter Greene, Amy Yasbeck, Richard Jeni and Cameron Diaz.
The plot follows Stanley Ipkiss (Carrey), a hapless and timid bank teller who finds an enchanted mask that transforms
him into a green-faced troublemaker who can cartoonishly alter himself and his surroundings at will.
It is the first film in the Mask franchise.
Principal photography began in Los Angeles on August
30, 1993, and concluded in October.
The film marked the acting debut of Diaz, who was a model with no acting experience prior to filming, while Carrey, who was starring on the sketch
comedy series In Living Color and had just wrapped filming on Ace Ventura: Pet Detective (1994), was virtually unknown at the time.
Their casting led to disputes from New Line Cinema executives who expressed concern that the film would be unsuccessful without
well-established actors, but the studio ultimately relented following reassurance from Russell that Carrey and Diaz were the right choices.
The Mask was theatrically released in the United States
on July 29, 1994, to positive reviews.
The film was a commercial success, grossing $352 million against its $18-23 million
production budget, becoming the fourth-highest-grossing film of 1994.
It also influenced the resurgence of swing music in the 1990s.
Carrey was nominated for Best Actor at the 52nd Golden Globe Awards and the film
was nominated for Best Visual Effects at the 67th Academy Awards.
A sequel, Son of the Mask, was released in 2005.
The film explores themes of dual identity, bank,
superhero, mockery, transformation.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional and mind_bending.